A Guide to the Records of the Governor's Office for Substance Abuse Prevention, 2001-2006 (bulk 2002-2005)
Library of Virginia
- Series IX. Transition Files, 2005., Extent: 1 folder. (Folder 24)
  This series is comprised exclusively of a transition notebook prepared for internal office usage. Transition notebooks are typically created for the benefit of new staff members who fill vacant positions. The purpose of a transition notebook is to provide new staff with enough information to immediately fit in with organizational culture and continue working towards predetermined goals. Accordingly, the Governor's Office for Substance Abuse transition notebook is a valuable resource for researchers because it provides an overview of the office's mission, values, budget, problem issues, and accomplishments at a set point in time. It also includes an organizational chart and employee biographical sketches. It appears to have been disassembled at some point and is missing eleven of its twelve appendices. Appendix F, Community Profile Database, is all that remains of the appendices section. The Community Profile Database is an online interactive database on the office website and is designed to allow website visitors to organize statistical information regarding Virginia youths by several choices of indicators and limiters.
  - Transition Notebook, December 1, 2005. (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Series X. Conference and Training Records, 2003-2005., Extent: 7 folders. (Folder 25-31)
  This series includes the conference and training records of programs administered by the Governor's Office for Substance Abuse Prevention. Most of this series is comprised of KidSafe conference packets containing conference schedules, topics, and PowerPoint handouts. The packets were presumably given to conference attendees to record notes. Registration information and letters written in gratitude by Marilyn P. Harris, Director of the Governor's Office for Substance Abuse Prevention, to individuals who helped bring about a given conference are included with some packets. Further information regarding the KidSafe program is available in Series VIII. Agency Publications and Supporting Documentation, 2002-2005.
  Also included in this series are records relating to the Governor's Youth Public Safety Advisory Council Summit, Gang Awareness and Intervention Training, and the Protect and Respect Statewide Summit. The Governor's Youth Public Safety Advisory Council Summit records include a press release, an events schedule, a list of attendees, and letters written in gratitude by Secretary of Public Safety John W. Marshall to individuals who helped bring about the summit. The Gang Awareness and Intervention Training records include a training schedule, memoranda addressed to presenters and written by Marilyn P. Harris, Director of the Governor's Office for Substance Abuse Prevention, and an event briefing paper. The records of the Protect and Respect Statewide Summit are limited to an agenda. This series is arranged chronologically. Further information regarding the Protect and Respect program can be found in Series XI. Project Files and Supporting Documentation, 2003-2005.
  - KidSafe Prevention Conference, November 19, 2003. (Box 1, Folder 25 (1 of 2))
  - KidSafe Prevention Conference, November 19, 2003. (Box 1, Folder 26 (2 of 2))
  - KidSafe Prevention Conference 2, November 4, 2004. (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - KidSafe Prevention Conference 3, November 16, 2005. (Box 1, Folder 28 (1 of 3))
  - KidSafe Prevention Conference 3, November 16, 2005. (Box 1, Folder 29 (2 of 3))
  - KidSafe Prevention Conference 3, November 16, 2005. (Box 1, Folder 30 (3 of 3))
  - Governor's Youth Public Safety Advisory Council (GYPSAC) Summit, June 30, 2004. (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Gang Awareness and Intervention Training, September 30, 2004. (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Protect and Respect Statewide Summit, May 12, 2005. (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Series XI. Project Files and Supporting Documentation, 2003-2005., Extent: 2 folders. (Folder 32-33)
  This series is comprised of what the Governor's Office for Substance Abuse Prevention refers to as project files. Records included in this series include records of the 2004 National Night Out Governor's Youth Essay Contest, the Interagency Anti-Gang Workgroup, and the Protect and Respect Program.
  National Night Out is a crime and drug prevention event sponsored by the National Association of Town Watch. The event is designed to heighten awareness about local anticrime efforts through a night of neighborhood activities and front porch vigils. The records of the National Night Out essay contest include a contest flyer, an entry form, a rule sheet containing guidelines and eligibility criteria, and a letter from Governor Mark R. Warner to an entrant who is in all likelihood the contest winner. A letter from Marilyn P. Harris, Director of the Governor's Office for Substance Abuse Prevention to a contest entrant offers thanks for having entered the contest.
  The Interagency Anti-Gang Workgroup is a consortium of Commonwealth agencies under the Public Safety Secretariat. It is tasked with sharing information and promoting anti-gang activities between member agencies. The Governor's Office for Substance Abuse Prevention is one member agency within the consortium. The records of the Interagency Anti-Gang Workgroup include notices for anti-gang workshops and a 2005 booklet outlining the goals and accomplishments of the workgroup.
  The records of the Protect and Respect program are the most extensive set of records in this series. Protect and Respect is a Governor's Office for Substance Abuse Prevention personal safety and awareness program for older Virginians. One aspect of Protect and Respect includes a mentoring program between older Virginians and adolescents. Records include a brochure outlining the purpose of the Protect and Respect program, an event program for the May 25, 2004 grand opening of the Protect and Respect Public Safety Institutes, two certificates noting the graduation of an individual enrolled in one of the Protect and Respect Public Safety Institutes, an event briefing information sheet, and PowerPoint presentations designed for both program grantees and those interested in the background and purpose of the Protect and Respect Intergenerational Mentoring Program. Also included is an independent needs assessment study done by an outside contractor and designed to identify crime issues affecting older Virginians. Further information on the Protect and Respect program can me found in Series III. Safe and Drug Free Schools and Communities Act of 2001 Grant Subaward Records, 2001-2006.
  - Protect and Respect, 2003-2005. (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Governor's Youth Essay Contest, 2004. (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Interagency Anti-Gang Workgroup, 2005. (Box 1, Folder 33)